<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conspiracie against kings, heauens scorne A sermon preached at Westminster-Abbey before the iudges, vpon the fifth of Nouemb. 1622. By Ro: Willan, Doctor in Diuinity.</title>
            <author>Willan, Robert, d. 1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120042</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855243</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20724</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20724)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1049:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conspiracie against kings, heauens scorne A sermon preached at Westminster-Abbey before the iudges, vpon the fifth of Nouemb. 1622. By Ro: Willan, Doctor in Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>Willan, Robert, d. 1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in a mortised ornament.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Insurgency --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CONSPIRACIE AGAINST KINGS, HEAVENS SCORNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon preached at</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Abbey <hi>before the Iudges, vpon</hi> the fifth of <hi>NOVEMB.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY RO: WILLAN,</hi> Doctor in Diuinity.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Sitotus orbis aduerſum me coniuraret, vt quippiam moliar aduerſus regiam Maieſtatem, ego tamen Deum timerem, &amp; ordinatum ab eo Regem offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere temerè non auderem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>BERN. Epiſt.</hi> 170. <hi>ad Ludouic. Franc. Regem.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by IOHN BILL.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND REVEREND FATHER IN God, IOHN, Lord Biſhop of</hi> Lincolne, <hi>Keeper of the great Seale.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great part of this Sermon is ſpent vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Quare:</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a <hi>Quare</hi> will be put to the Sermon it ſelfe; that in <hi>Iob, Quare miſero data eſt lux?</hi> why doth this poore Labour behold the light? I can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer nothing, but the Reuerend Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, before whom it was bound to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vpon tryall, adiudged it to be preſſed. Appealing to the Chancery, ſo great vnion and harmony is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb facs="tcp:20724:3"/> the Courts, no reuerſing of the Doome was to be had there. So Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Gratitude, and Modestie ſtriuing together, the laſt could not alone make her party good against two. Obedience pleaded, that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is diſſolued, when ſullen ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence poſſeſſes ſuch as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſpeake, (or print, all is one.) Gratitude aduiſed me by an <hi>Emboliſme,</hi> or <hi>intercalation,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert my priuate thankefulneſſe among the publike gratulations of all men, ſome for redreſſe of their wrongs, ſome for the diſpatch of their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſuites, ſome for faire denyall of their vniust petitions, accounting your Lordſhip another <hi>Cato,</hi> of whom they durst not aske any thing irregular; the good reioycing to ſee,
<pb facs="tcp:20724:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> as the <hi>Athenians</hi> ſent out their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laminian ſhip, ſwift and ſure, in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſeaſons: ſo this acedious and corrupt Age, incountred with your aſsiduous and actiue integritie, the moſt curious interpreters of great actions, euen thoſe, who wiſhed not ſuch honour to your profeſsion, dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it an Egyptian ſpoyle, (and a myſterie diſcloſed, that a Gouernour might be choſen out of <hi>Rome)</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing, where many were thought capable of high place, vntill they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, <hi>Imperio proditus infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior;</hi> your Lordſhip by the aſsiſtance of His grace, which will conduct you to the races end, hath ſatisfied, if not exceeded, expectation. Then Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, tho blushing at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthines, yet hoping to ſhun the cenſure of
<pb facs="tcp:20724:4"/> ouer-forwardneſſe, neuer adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but <hi>Candidior poſtquam tondenti barba cadebat,</hi> conſented to tender it vnto your protection; <hi>Nil illum amplexa verebor.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe then from your firſt Chaplaine, theſe firſt Fruites, <hi>&amp; capitur mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo thuris honore Deus.</hi> When God gaue his people an harueſt of fruites, hee reſerued to himſelfe a ſheafe of thankes; ſuch a ſheafe for the harueſt of fauour and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is this, accompanied with prayers to that high God, who giues <hi>ſalutem ſublimium orationibus humilium,</hi> ſtill to multiply his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vpon you, and giue you the true happines of this and a better life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble and thankfull ſeruant, RO. WILLIAN.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Greſham Coll.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 4.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Why did the Gentiles rage, and the people meditate a vaine thing?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>The Kings of the earth ſtood vp, and the Rulers tooke counſell together against the Lord, and against his Anoynted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Let vs breake their bonds a ſunder, and caſt their cords from vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>He that dwelleth in the heauens ſhall laugh them to ſcorne; the Lord ſhall haue them in deriſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text like <hi>Ianus</hi> looks backward and forward: Backe, to reuiue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of this Day; t'was a day of conſpiracie, and this is a Text of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie: Forward, to repreſent the face of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20724:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> the times preſent; tumultuarie times, and this is a tumultuarie Text. Although, bleſſed be God, and the care of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, we inioy Halcion dayes, yet it is not ſo in other Chriſtian parts of the world. They haue found them (pardon the word) Dogge-dayes; it is <hi>Tertullians Canicula perſecutionis.</hi> Such is the furie and rage of one againſt another, that the fume and ſmoke thereof prognoſticates the fire * of conſlagration, ready to breake <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Naz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat.</hi> 3. <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> foorth to conſume all. When the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were forbidden to preach in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Name of Ieſus, they tooke their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement out of this Pſalme. Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Luther,</hi> when all the world was in oppoſition againſt him, found his beſt comfort in this Pſalme. Why ſhould I (ſayes he) be <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> when God is <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius?</hi> or vexe my ſelfe with diſcontent, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ep. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when God vouchſafes to be merrie, and laughes at their vaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. We our ſelues may make a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſe of this Pſalme: To raiſe vp our thankfulneſſe for our owne happy deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20724:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> paſt, and our peaceable eſtate preſent, while others ſtruggle againſt <hi>luctantes ventos tempestateſque ſonoras,</hi> and withall be affected to compaſſionate the contrition of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to vnfold the words; wiſhing I had Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his facultie, <note place="margin">In Pſalmis Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidis explican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis eius lyram &amp; plectrum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur mutuatus Poſſeuin. Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note> * who in the expoſition of <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalms, is ſaid to haue borrowed <hi>Dauids</hi> owne Harpe; ſo properly hee expreſt his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>The Text may bee conſidered three wayes: As a Propheſie, as an Hiſtorie, as an Embleme. <hi>Dauid</hi> repreſents a threefold perſon, his Sauiours, his owne, and ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was no ſooner deſigned King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Iſrael, but the bordering Nations, and the ten Tribes made head and conſpired. What he ſaw acted againſt his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he foreſaw in the eye of Propheſie ſhould be accompliſhed vpon his Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. For ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> vpon the fore-named place, applies theſe words of the Pſalme, to the Paſſion of our Lord Ieſus. As an Embleme it fitteth this day, wherein
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20724:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and vtter ſubuerſion of this flouriſhing Kingdome was intended.</p>
            <p>The parts of the Text are two: Firſt, <hi>Dauids</hi> hard plight and condition. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Dauids</hi> ſweet comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The firſt in two particulars: 1. A conſpiracie: 2. the cauſe of it. In the conſpiracie, obſerue the actors, and the managing. The actors, all ſorts of men; the baſeſt, and the choiceſt ſpirits, the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and the vulgar; euery one hath a hand in it. The managing is deſcribed in foure Verbes, Raging, Meditating, Banding, Plotting: ſo it hath foure fearefull ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters, Malice, Induſtrie, Power, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie.</p>
            <p>The cauſe none on <hi>Dauids</hi> part, for that is implyed in the Prophets <hi>Quare:</hi> The motiue on his enemies part, <hi>Let vs breake their bonds aſunder, and caſt the yoke from vs:</hi> I, there it is; The cauſe of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the diſlike of Gouernment; they will not brooke either State, or Church, no Law, no Religion. The ſecond part; <hi>Dauids</hi> conſolation, and that two-fold;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20724:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> within him, without him. Firſt, the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of his owne conſcience, that no ambition of his owne, made him aſpire to a Crowne, but God called him, and the Prophet anointed him. Without, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of heauen; God looked vpon him with an eye of fauour; vpon his enemies with an eye of ſcorne, <hi>Hee that dwelleth in the heauens ſhall laugh them to ſcorne.</hi> A dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſcription of God; by a Periphraſis of the place of his abode, <hi>He dwels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> By a Proſopopeia, attributing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly, but ſignificantly, a ſplen and laughter vnto God. So the Cataſtrophe and concluſion of all conſpiracie, is the Sarcaſmos, and bitter ſcorne of God.</p>
            <p>Neither is the ingemination of the word a needleſſe tautologie, but an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifying Emphaſis, <hi>repetens iterum ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque monebat,</hi> doubling the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to beware how men fall by rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt God his Anointed, into ſuch a degree of miſerie, as to be contemned of God.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Text as a Propheſie.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20724:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> The old fiction of the Gyants warre is heere repreſented in a true action. The petie Potentates of the earth are in armes againſt the graund Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, who if he thunders, the greateſt of them tremble, and with <hi>Tiberius</hi> flie for defence, to the poore refuge of a Laurell wreath. If he makes the earth to ſhake, What priuiledge haue their Palaces, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the meaneſt cottages? will the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels come at their call, or the Sunne ſhine at their commaund? Nay, come lower, in the ayre beyond a <hi>Nimrods</hi> tower they cannot build, which the birds will flie ouer. In earth is their dominion; and that limited, circumſcribed; their bounds dooled out by him whom they oppoſe. The Perſian Monarchie did not paſſe the narrow Helleſpont. The Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian neuer had one foot in Africa, nor the Romane beyond Euphrates. Ouer men they rule, neither thoſe which are paſt, nor thoſe which are to haue beeing, not ouer one whole man; the body they may deſtroy, the ſoule is out of their reach;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20724:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> they cannot compell the will, nor alter the affection of the meaneſt. What For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then can you bring into the field? weigh your ſtrength. Are you able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt his power, from whom your owne is deriued? no ſurely, this rebellion is not directly intended againſt God, but his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed Ieſus Chriſt; 'tis a miſtake, they cannot be ſeuered. He that doth not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Sonne, doeth not honour the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who ſent him; 'tis againſt both, but eſpecially againſt King Ieſus: a King indeed, euen as a man, by moſt iuſt title; the Deitie being vnited to the humanitie, gaue him right ouer all things; hauing purchaſed the world by the effuſion of his blood, he is abſolute Lord ouer it; his humiliation promerited this exaltation, and being the naturall Sonne of God, he obtained it as his patrimonie.</p>
            <p>Is he a King? what are the Enſignes of his authoritie? where is his crowne? not like <hi>Dauids</hi> which he raught from <hi>Hada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rezers</hi> head: that was of pearle, his of thornes, which <hi>mille puncturis,</hi> with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20724:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtings pierced his royall head. Yet S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſees not onely many crownes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that head, but all crownes caſt at his feete. Is he a King? where is his throne? not like Solomons of Iuory; his was of wood, the Croſſe; <hi>Dominus regnauit a ligno.</hi> The malitious Iewes raſed the laſt words out of the Text, <note n="*" place="margin">Iuſtin Mart. Triph. Tertull. aduer. Mar.</note> yet by the Title they ſet vp, they acknowledged his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigntie, and their owne rebellion. <hi>Quem Iſrael crucifixit vt maleficum,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Clement Alex.</note> 
               <hi>coronauit vt regem,</hi> VVhom they crucified as a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, they ſtiled a King. Is he a King? where is his court? beſides that in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in the hearts of his choſen, there hee keepes reſidence. Is he a King? where lies his Exchequer, and reuenewes? not like <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who taxed all the world, and did no more then hee might. Tribute is Princes due, as markes of their power, ſinewes of their maintenance, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of their labours. But this King <hi>exinaniuit ſeipſum,</hi> did emptie himſelfe to in rich his ſubiects, and out of the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his mercie paid all their ſcores: as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20724:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Elias</hi> gaue the widow oyle enough to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her creditors, and to liue beſide; ſo this King beſtowed vpon vs his ſorrowes and obedience, to cancell the hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt vs, together with the rich ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of his grace, which well imployed will make vs liue for euer. The Tribute he requires, is praiſe and honour of his holy Name; the rent hee cals for, is faith in his merits; the homage he expects, is obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Lawes. His Lawes, what are they? <hi>Mandata eius non ſunt grauia,</hi> His commandements are not grieuous; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he teacheth is trueth, what hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynes is righteouſneſſe, what he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth is happines; and yet againſt this King, <hi>Dauid</hi> fore-ſees this great tumult and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. No ſooner did this King diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play his banners, ſo <hi>Eſay</hi> cals it, <note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>In ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num populorum,</hi> for a ſigne to the people, to muſter vp the world to an holy warre, againſt the deuill and ſinne, but preſently they band to ouerthrow his ſtandard, and to teare his colours. <hi>Eſay</hi> his <hi>Signum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulorum,</hi> becomes <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 2.</note> 
               <hi>Simeon</hi> his <hi>Signum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictionis.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20724:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> It is a Metaphor from Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, who ſet vp a marke to ſhoote at, and ſtriue to ſticke their ſhafts in the very center of it: Such a marke was King <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> vpon whom both Iewes and Gentiles did emptie all their quiuers. <hi>Herod</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther began the leading ſhoote with a deadly arrow, to entrap the life of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his cradle: hee cauſed fourteene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand infants to be put to death, but miſſed his aime. <hi>Herod</hi> the ſonne ſhot at him an arrow of ſcorne, and mocked him. The Prieſts and people ſhot at him an arrow of accuſation, <hi>Gens tua &amp; Pontifices tuj ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant te;</hi> &amp; Pilate the Roman Iudge ſhot the vp-ſhot of condemnation: but as ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly <hi>Ambroſe, Abſoluit iudicio, condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit mysterio,</hi> He abſolued him in his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and condemned him in a myſterie; What myſterie? this of the Text, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and the people, Iewes and Gentiles, the vulgar and ruler, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate, Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiaphas</hi> conſpired againſt King <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere is the accompliſhment of this Prophecie, once fulfilled in <hi>Chriſt</hi> our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20724:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Head, euer to be fulfilled in the Church, and his members. As long as it continues vpon earth it ſhall euer bee haunted with one of theſe three Furies; 1. Perſecution, 2. Varietie of opinions. 3. The vnanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conuerſation of Chriſtians to the rule preſcribed. Sometime Tyrants ſeeke to deuoure the Church, and to roote vp the ſeedes of truth, not onely thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her pale, but in her boſome. <note n="*" place="margin">Del Rio Adag. Sacru.</note> The Monke, who ambitious of Martyrdome told the Souldan, that hee was come into his Court, to die for preaching the truth, was anſwered, (I wiſh it had not beene true) hee needed not haue trauelled ſo far for death; For he might eaſily finde it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Princes at home: but force ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer got ground of truth: all tempters of that kind were inforced to confeſſe with the cruell Queene, <hi>Ego proſum ſola nocendo. Hereſies</hi> indeed haue done more miſchiefe by deflouring pure doctrine; ſome ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, as made Chriſtianitie ridiculous to wiſe men; ſome ſo wretched, as made Chriſtianitie reiected by honeſt men. Oh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20724:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſtian Religion, the cleare fountaine of peace and vnion, how doe thy diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions turne thee into a puddle of quarels and contentions! How are thy Wels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Eſek</hi> and <hi>Sitnah;</hi> thy Waters, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribah,</hi> that wert <hi>Siloe,</hi> flowing in a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle current! Thy ſacred Scripture is made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Thy bleſſed Sacrament, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thy reuerend Name, the maske of warre, and vaile of ſedition; *thy diſſenſions por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Nazian. orat.</hi> 1. <hi>de pace.</hi>
               </note> thy diſſolution. Had not thy Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our inclined the heart of one by his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, as with a <hi>Lituus,</hi> or Augurall ſtaffe and Warder, to ſtint &amp; ſtay the ouer-nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hands of begun furie, as the Angel did <hi>Abrahams,</hi> that monſter the ſword, whoſe gliſtring face flaſhed foorth lightnings of terrour, with blood-ſhotten eyes wildly ſtaring, his ſteelie handes offering rough embracements, his waſtefull feere wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring about thy pleaſant borders, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hauocke and deſolation, his Whale-like mouth wide open to ſwallow thee vp, had ſurfetted of thy fleſh, and beene drunken with thy blood. To ſuch a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20724:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> miſerable ſtate wert thou brought, by renting of <hi>Chriſts</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacramento veſt is vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Eccleſiae conſignauit. Cyprian.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> indiuiſible garment, which the ſouldiers forbare to teare in ſunder. As the Prophet of <hi>Iudah,</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the number of thy Cities, are thy gods, O <hi>Iudah:</hi> ſo of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Countries, ſo many ſeuerall opinions.</p>
            <p>But aboue all Rebels againſt our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed king <hi>Ieſus,</hi> thoſe for number exceed, who acknowledge him for their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, and deny him obedience, who embrace his Faith, and by their ſinfull liues, tread the blood of his Couenant vnder their feete. <note n="*" place="margin">Non eſt vera fides quae verbo credit, &amp; mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit. Greg.</note> It is no true faith, when the life confutes the faith. If wee be Subiects, why doe wee liue, as Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawes? If his Diſciples, why is our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation contrary to his Diſcipline, as though wee were trained vp vnder <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus,</hi> or <hi>Mahomet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue done with the Text as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie; onely I muſt put the <hi>Quare</hi> to it: And I finde among the Expoſitors, a threefold <hi>Quare;</hi> 1. of Inquiſition. 2. of Admiration. 3. of Reprehenſion.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20724:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> If the <hi>Quare</hi> bee put in generall termes, how comes it to paſſe that there are ſuch ſtirs, tumults and garboyles in the world, ſuch and ſo great, as if God did not ſit at the helme? The queſtion is hard, and preſſed too farre, may prooue curious. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth that this <hi>Quare,</hi> after it had rackt and tortured him to finde out the cauſe of euill, turned him into a Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chean heretique. <hi>Solomon</hi> tels vs that the locks of the Spouſe are curled, &amp; his haire blacke as a Rauen. The ſecrets of Gods prouidence are curled and intortled, wee cannot vnfold them; his haire blacke, his wayes paſt finding out. Though he bee in himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to vs he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; he dwels in light, but ſuch light as no man can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto. The modeſt and ſhort anſwer to this <hi>Quare,</hi> is that of the Schoole, In particular adminiſtrations, a prouident <note place="margin">Thomas.</note> Ruler preuenteth, what in him lies, all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences: but in the vniuerſall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, it ſeemed beſt to Diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſuffer ſome euill, not for want of power to hinder it, but out of his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20724:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> goodneſſe. If God did not ſuffer ſome euill, wee ſhould want much good; The good of his iuſtice and mercy, which ſhine foorth in his ſeuere iudgements, in his gracious indulgence. Goodneſſe had not bin ſo illuſtrated; her oppoſite makes it more amiable. And as out of the ſalt brackiſh Sea ſweete ſhowres are exhaled: ſo from euill, the Almighty his power drewe the dewes of grace in our Lord IESVS. And this is as much as I dare adde to the <hi>Quare</hi> of Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Quare?</hi> why ſhould the good and vertuous be alwayes oppoſed and expoſed to the furie and malice of cruell men? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this is <hi>res mira,</hi> ſtrange &amp; marueilous, but not <hi>res noua,</hi> any new matter. It was thus from the beginning. No ſooner was God worſhipped and ſerued, but hatred <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inuidiam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tita eſt religio.</hi> Auguſt.</note> and ſpite fell to the lotte and portion of Religion. The firſt man who pleaſed God <note place="margin">Liuor ſacrificij ſeminarium fratricidij.</note> was ſlaine; the acceptable ſacrifice was the ſeminary of death. It can bee no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, diſsimilitude and diſtance of maners breede alienation of affections. There is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20724:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> nothing doeth ſo condemne the liues of the wicked, as the conuerſation of the godly, the fatte kine make the leane ſeeme more il-fauoured; hence their rage and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage behauiour: beſides, 'tis the pleaſure of God thus to try and honour his Saints, and to produce their patience. What pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures could <hi>Apelles</hi> draw? did he want a table to work vpon? What building could the <hi>Architect</hi> reare without ſtones, timber, and materials? This is enough to ſtay the <hi>Quare</hi> of Admiration.</p>
            <p>3. What is it you goe about? It is to no purpoſe; you <hi>imagine a vaine thing, vaine</hi> impoſſibly, <hi>vaine</hi> vnprofitably. No wreſtling of man can euacuate the <note place="margin">Diuinum conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium dum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatur, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletur, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſapientia dum reluctatur comprehenditur Greg.</note> purpoſe of God. Whileman ſtruggles, he is caught, and by reſiſting the wil of God, hee doth fulfill it. Second cauſes are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of impediment, as the burning of fire by the action of water: but there is no euaſion to ſhun the Decree of heauen. All wretched indeauours againſt Chriſt and his choſen, are like <hi>Caligula</hi> his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, who neuer tooke any thing in hand
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20724:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> if there were hope to effect it; 'tis <hi>vaine</hi> impoſſibly.</p>
            <p>And what profit can ariſe? hee doeth a ſhrewd turne who gaines by it. To count euill for gaine, is vniuſt, but humane: but miſchiefe intended for miſchiefes ſake, is Deuiliſh. The old way of trecheries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at <hi>quid proderit nobis?</hi> as in the caſe of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But now adayes a new ſinne is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nouum &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aeſtimabile, in plurimis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſt, parum alicui eſt, ſi ipſe ſit faelix, niſi alter fuerit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faelix. Saluianus de Prouid.</hi> 5.</note> hatcht and rife with many; they cannot be pleaſed to liue in quiet themſelues, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they diſturbe the tranquillity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. As vipers and the venimous Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharides and ſtinging ſpiders, are more deteſtable then beares or wolues, becauſe they ſting folke to death without any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; So that is an odious deſigne which is <hi>vaine</hi> improfitably.</p>
            <p>And now I paſſe from the Sunne to the ſhadow; from the Propheticall conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt CHRIST our King, to the Hiſtoricall faction againſt King <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The people rage.</hi> For people in any eſtate to grumble againſt Gouernours, is no nouelty: neuer was any Gouernour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20724:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo prouident or happy, as to eſchew the furious clamour of ſome vnbrideled and impetuous ſpirits. A King that hath a great multitude to gouerne, might as ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Tutior eſses pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor vrſorum &amp; Tigridum. Petrarch.</note> be a keeper of Beares and Tigers. The Lion will kiſſe his keeper, the Elephant will bee ruled and ledde about by a little dwarfe; but man is an indomable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>If you recount the Fate of kings, more <note place="margin">Curtius.</note> haue beene indangered by the practiſes of their owne people, then by outward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility. As it was ſaid of <hi>Seianus;</hi> ſo of the people; They are as weyward, when plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as when oppoſed.</p>
            <p>Among thoſe who conſpired againſt <hi>Ceſar,</hi> there were more whom he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by benefits, then exaſperated by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries. I, but this is the lot of ſome oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Princes, whoſe gouernement make the people ſigh. Nay, the beſt that euer were, haue found enough to do, to keepe the people in good order. Meeke <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſhun a ſhowre of ſtones, is glad to take ſanctuary, and flie to the Tabernacle.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20724:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Good <hi>Dauid</hi> is not free from rebelling <hi>Sheba,</hi> reuiling <hi>Shimei;</hi> and, as the text tels vs, the people rage at him. No King like <hi>Dauid;</hi> the Scripture propoundes him as a patterne to Princes. When it honours the good, they are <hi>ſicut Dauid:</hi> when it blames the degenerated, <hi>non ſicut Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt, deſcribing the genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of our Sauiour, from how many Kings he was deſcended, vouchſafes none of them the ſtile and title of a King but <note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> and him twiſe in one verſe. For a literall and a moral reaſon; partly, becauſe hee was the firſt King, ſetling and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the kingdome of Iſrael; but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, for that hee was indued with all princely qualities of iuſtice, wiſedome, clemencie, courage and deuotion. Yet ſee heere the vnruly people rage at him.</p>
            <p>And not onely the giddie people, but the Rulers. It was a good Embleme of <note place="margin">Farneſius.</note> the Cardinall, deſcribing the booteleſſe attempts of an vnguided multitude, a Beech tree with the top off, the Motto, <hi>Ruina reliqui;</hi> for as that tree withers when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20724:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> it is lopped, ſo multitudes vaniſh without leaders, and become a burden vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and a prey vnto others. Therefore the Rulers come in. As the Planets in theſe <hi>Epicicles</hi> or little <hi>orbes</hi> are carryed ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularly againſt the heauenly motion: ſo ſometimes pettie greatneſſe is prone to ſtray from their duty toward their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, if either the rayes of fauour fall not ſo directly vpon themſelues, or vpon others more then they wiſh. For although <note place="margin">Principi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> est virtus maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, noſſe ſuos.</note> Princes can beſt iudge of the fitneſſe, worth, and fidelitie of their owne inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and, like the Sunne, ſhine more brightly vpon a cleare ſmooth glaſſe, then vpon an vneuen clod, neither apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue nor reflect the beames: yet as in building, ſo in States, the turret ouer-loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the bordering houſes, is wiſhed downe, and the hand diſliked that ſet it vp. If <hi>Dauid</hi> make but a feaſt to <hi>Abner, Ioab</hi> will expoſtulate with him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times men of high ſpirit and meane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes will diſtemper <hi>Dauids</hi> peace, ſowing diſſenſions among the Nobles: The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20724:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> contentions of prime men being their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Curio nil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit in cenſu, praeter diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum.</hi> Plin.</note> onely reuenue. Perhaps they will take pet, if the ſecret affaires be not imparted, when their open boſomes full of chinkes are no caskes to containe them. <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> would not reueale, being asked of his owne ſonne, what time hee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue his campe, but ſaid, the ſound of the trumpet ſhould giue them notice. It is enough if <hi>Dauid</hi> vouchſafe to diſcloſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ardnum nimis eſt meruiſſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis, vbi ſi quid cognoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur prodi, vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b alio, formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Caſſiod. variar. 8. cap. 10.</note> himſelfe to his faithfull <hi>Cuſhais,</hi> whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be pretended. Diſobedience in a vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar man, may admit vulgar apologies: but in a ruler, or man of qualitie, it is a decom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſinne; the example more ſpreading and contagious; their eminencie makes it more conſpicuous. Obſerue how fitly the Prophet ſpeakes; he attributes rage to the vulgar, power and policie to the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. They <hi>meditate, band,</hi> and <hi>plot:</hi> A word of each verbe.</p>
            <p>They <hi>meditate:</hi> All ſinne is painefull <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and laborious, the Poet was deceiued, when he ſaid, <hi>Facilis deſcenſus Auerni,</hi> the way thither is of hard acceſſe. The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20724:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> make their paſſage thorow ſtonie rockes of hardneſſe and penurie. The am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious clambers vp ſteepe hils, and crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie mountaines, to get a place as ſlipperie and tickle, as the chaire of <hi>Eli.</hi> The vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous tramples in durt and mire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkling himſelfe with ſhame and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The Reuengefull breakes through hedges ſtucke with thornes, making him all gore and blood. The Enuious walkes <note place="margin">* Quot bona faelicium, tot tormenta inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum. Seneca.</note> in darke and ſhadie places, that hee may not ſee an others happineſſe. But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the ſinne of Miſchiefe, is a vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, painefull, indefatigable ſinne. <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> will bee awake when <hi>Peter</hi> is aſleepe: the Tare-ſower in the field, when the Husbandman is in his bed; 'tis their care, ſtudie, meditation.</p>
            <p>Againe, obſerue what a cowardly thing ſinne is. <hi>Eue</hi> had no ſooner offended, but ſhee ſought out a fellow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion. Vpon <hi>Caine</hi> his cruell deſignes, how hee trembled and quaked, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none in the world to feare but his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and ſiſters; yet hee thought in euery
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20724:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> buſh an ambuſh laid for him. All ſinne is timerous, but aboue all, the ſinne of Conſpiracie. The ten Patriarkes durſt not ſet vpon one <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> without a <hi>venite oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidamus.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Plut. in vita. Agid.</hi>
               </note> They who are moſt ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers of order and gouernment, and fearefull to offend lawes, are moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and couragious in a iuſt cauſe. But Conſpiracie is a ſin of ſuch ougly ſhape, and horrid repreſentation, as the partie dares neuer looke vpon himſelfe ſingle and alone, but runnes as a deere to the herd; then they troope and band. And becauſe power not directed is but armed follie, they take counſell together. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, marke their ſecrecie: together, marke their vnitie: Counſell to a deſigne, is as the foundation to a building; ſecrecie ſeales it ſafely vp. Mines, if they bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, returne vpon the enginer; and coles moulder to aſhes, if the ſunne ſhine vpon them. The Conſpirator learned this Leſſon well, who being asked his knowledge, anſwered, If I had knowne <note place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius apud Senec.</note> it, you had neuer knowne it.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20724:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And if vnitie keepe them not toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all is marred I he diuiſion of Iordan makes a paſſage to the Arke; the disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a faction is the ouerthrow of it. <hi>Cyrus</hi> comming to Euphrates, found the ſwelling riuer impaſſable, diuiding it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three hundred ſtreames, it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable euery where: but <hi>Dauids</hi> Rebels ſticke cloſe, and <hi>take counſell together.</hi> By this time you perceiue <hi>Dauids</hi> hard caſe, and indeed the caſe is very hard.</p>
            <p>There be two Pillars of Gouernment; Direction, in the Superiour; Obedience, in the Inferiour: the Eye to ſee, the Eare to heare, God made both, ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20.</note> When theſe meet, the State is ſuccesfull; diuorced, nothing right. The Grecians expreſt this well in the Marriage <hi>Iupiter</hi> made betweene <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the child brought forth betweene them was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aeſchilus.</hi>
               </note> When authoritie is married to obedience, the fruite of that match is happineſſe: It was not now ſo with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and yet the worſt is behinde, for I muſt put the <hi>Quare</hi> once againe. Wherefore is all this malice,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20724:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> this ſtir, combining and plotting? it is for all, <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> the ſafety of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the ſecuritie of his State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>They will breake the bands aſunder, and caſt the yoke from them.</hi> By bands, all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters vnderſtand good Lawes. By <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us &amp;</hi> 70 <hi>Inter.</hi>
               </note> the yoke, ſome allude vnto Religion, that ſweet and eaſie yoke of Chriſt; nor is the Metaphor vnfit. A yoke and collar doe bowe the necke, and Religion tames the ſtubburne nature of man, and makes him yeelde due obedience; It is the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſocietie, and ſtrongeſt Pillar of Gouernment.</p>
            <p>I begin at the <hi>Bands:</hi> The Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is a Tabernacle or Tent; pitcht vp to ſhelter men from wrong and iniurie, that they may liue happily together: Lawes are the cordes of it; breake the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 10. 20.</note> cords the Tent falles; <hi>My Tabernacle is fallen, my cordes are broken.</hi> Lawes are Bandes, for the wilde, to cicure them and humble them, for the weake to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and keepe them: as in Vines, they are vnder-propped and bound vp, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20724:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> make them fruitfull in veſſels, they are hooped to containe liquor: ſo Lawes are bonds to hold the euil in awe, &amp; the good in ſafety. They binde all without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſpeake not of Princes, Lawes were <note place="margin">Leges Principi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nemo ſcripſit Plin.</note> not written for them; Lawes do not, like death, equall the Scepter with the ſpade: yet as it was ſaid of the bleſſed Virgin, offering her legall ſacrifice for her Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Supra legem fecerat gratia, ſub lege humilitas;</hi> ſo of good Princes, their high Calling makes them aboue Law, their humilitie reſpects it.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake before an Honourable Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, before Him, <hi>cuius dignatur ab ore Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar in orbe loqui,</hi> and thoſe whom our <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> hath made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Guardians, and Preſidents of his Lawes. Take care, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, of the Cordes, for danger of the Tabernacle; Your innocencie will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my humble boldneſſe <hi>(audacem facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat amor)</hi> doe not your ſelues breake <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> bands. The Law is good, ſaith the Apoſtle, but take it together, if it be vſed lawfully, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Suffer not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20724:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be verified, Lawes which are vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins <note place="margin">Leges in cala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> virgines, in for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meretric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the penning, become ſtrumpets in the pleading; and that they doe, if either they bee too much proſtituted by vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tongues, or wreſted and peruerted by any ſiniſter interpretation. It was the <note place="margin">Chilo apud Plut.</note> wiſe mans ſpeech; That Common wealth is beſt, where the Lawes are more heard then the Orators. Let the Law bee a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to the oppreſſed, no ſhambles for the innocent: A lanthorne to guide, no labyrinth to wander in: A hauen for harbour, no rocke to daſh vpon. How will you anſwere it to your <hi>Dauid,</hi> heere; to the Lord of <hi>Dauid,</hi> hereafter; if you vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate what he hath charged you to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</p>
            <p>For the people, Lawes are to them a threefold bond, for their liues, their eſtates, their conuerſation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their liues in the protection of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> Lawes. Life is of all naturall things the moſt excellent. Looke into Nature: We ſee in plants the roote, where life lies, is hidden in the ground to preſerue it; in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20724:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> beaſtes, the Serpent fenceth his head, in man, the very fabricke and conſtitution of his body expreſſes it. Mans heart, the fountaine of life, is not only incloſed with a thicke ſkin or filme, but inuironed with a ſtrong wall of ribs. And as Anatomiſts <note place="margin">Pliny.</note> doe obſerue, the bones about the heart do beare the faſhion and repreſentation of a ſword to defend it. Life is ſuch a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as the happy man deſires to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and the miſerable man is vnwilling to forgoe it. Imagine then you heare <hi>Dauids</hi> people ſpeaking vnto you, as the Captaine ouer fifty to <hi>Elias; Let our liues bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in your eyes;</hi> keepe the bond of life, as God did the tree of life with a flaming ſword to guard it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their eſtates and liuelihoods. The power ouer it is in the King, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quicquid ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet locuples, quicquid cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit auarus, Iure quidem noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, populo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edimus, vſum. Gunterus. Quod haec villa mea eſt, illa tua, ex iure Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum eſt. Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſt. tract.</hi> 6. <hi>in Iohannem.</hi>
               </note> the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his Subiects, the tuition in his Laws, the fruition their owne. Vnleſſe <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> enioy his lands, and <hi>Naboth</hi> his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent patrimony, euery one ſits in peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his owne Vine and figtree, the bond for eſtates is broken.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20724:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> 3. The bond of morality in conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <note place="margin">Plena turbis, &amp; turpitudini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Saluianus.</note> What a field I haue now, might I expatiate? It may bee ſaid of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as of <hi>Carthage,</hi> It is as full of ſinne as of people. And as the father ſaid of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Quot vlcera, tot ora Auſtin.</note> So many ſores, ſo many mouthes calling for pity and helpe. The idleneſſe, drunkenneſſe, pride, and all manner of diſſolute licenciouſneſſe, are ſo many tongues crying out, that the bond of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality is broken.</p>
            <p>Now the yoke is Religion, the ſoule and life of gouernement, without which it cannot proſper and flouriſh. It was a vaine conceit of the Emperour, who refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <note place="margin">Baſsianu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the name of <hi>Pius,</hi> would bee called <hi>Faelix,</hi> Happy, and not godly. There can bee no felicity but in appearance, where God is not truely ſerued; <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſes of this life, and that which is to come.</hi> A yoke by the grace and mercy of God we haue caſt off, <hi>Iugum oneris,</hi> a burden neither wee nor our fathers were able to endure. They tooke our ſiluer, and gaue vs no bread, emptied our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20724:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſtarued our ſoules. A yoke wee haue imbraced, the Doctrine of IESVS CHRIST purely and frequently taught; put wee our feete into the linkes, and our neckes into the chaine, bow wee downe our ſhoulders vnto it and beare it. Let vs <note place="margin">Eccl. 6. 23.</note> neuer bee weary of the bandes; at the laſt we ſhall finde reſt in it, and that ſhall bee turned into our ioy.</p>
            <p>Neuer could any King or Gouernour containe all their people vnder the yoke of one and the ſame Religion. Not <hi>Adam</hi> in his little Kingdome, great in circuit, ſmall in number of perſons; difference in ſo fewe increaſeth the difficulty of the worke. Not <hi>Noah</hi> in his octonary family. Not <hi>Moſes</hi> inueſted with extraordinary power of working miracles, apt to gaine credite and beliefe. The Iſraelites in his time followed ſtrange gods, <hi>Belphegor</hi> &amp; <hi>Moloch.</hi> What hath not our good <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> religious care indeauoured to keepe this yoke from being caſt off? By his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; what priuate man doth more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently tread in the Courts of the Lord,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20724:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> or viſit his Temple? What Prince did euer ſo teach his Courtiers to pray? By his writings? What reaſonable man ſees not the force of his arguments? <hi>Sybilla</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied of Antichriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that papers ſhould be his deſtruction; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie is fulfilled in his MAIESTIES papers: and of him may the aduerſaries of his Religion ſay, as <hi>Charles</hi> the fift of <hi>Luther, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus homo nobis ſcribendo perdide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat rem.</hi> As for the obiection, that the edge of the Law ſeemes to be blunted, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as imbrace not this yoke, 'tis light; for many times a contrary winde driues a ſhip into a ſafer port then it ſail'd vnto. Relaxation may doe that good, which rigour could not; truce begets <note place="margin">Tempus inane peto, requiem, ſpatiumque furori, Dum mea me vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam doceat fortuna dolere.</note> peace, reſpite aſſwageth rage, and calmes the ſtormes of vnquiet mindes. Whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer time diſcouers fauour to incourage the ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> whether he bee Guelph, or Gibiline, Papiſt or Puritan, he wil find the wheele turned vpon thoſe that ſeeke to turne the wheele of our Church-proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. By his laſt heauenly directions, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20724:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> followed well, may place Religion where it is not, and ſettle it where it is already entertain'd. He who is not moued by his example, nor inſtructed by his works, nor wonne by his clemency, nor obſeruant and pliable to his direction, I doe not ſay reſiſts, but argues and makes doubts, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring where no feare is, is a plaine rebell to CHRIST in heauen, to <hi>Dauid</hi> on earth. <note place="margin">Intonante Dei praecepto, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendum, non diſputandum. Austin.</note> For when Gods precept thunders, and that is when the voyce of his Deputie ſpeakes, we muſt ſubmit and not diſpute or els the yoke is caſt off.</p>
            <p>In the laſt gaſpe of allotted time I proceed to the laſt part of the text, <hi>Dauids</hi> comfort twofold. Within he ſtands vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his innocency, that hee was no intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor ſought the kingdome by any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill artes; the right owner placed him in it, he was Gods anointed. I paſſe the word handled already by him, <hi>cui doctior orbis ſubmiſsis defert faſcibus imperium.</hi> Onely this word held vp <hi>Dauids</hi> head in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and may be a ſure comfort, not only to <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſupreme, but to euery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20724:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> whom God rayſeth vp, they muſt meete with much difficulty and more enuie. But as he neuer manageth a place happily, who comes to it indire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly: ſo when God giues authority, hee giues ability to vndergoe the firſt, and a cleere conſcience will beare out the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>His outward comfort is from heauen. <hi>Hee that dwelleth in the heauens,</hi> That is a cheering word, from thence all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deſcend, from thence deliuery out of all danger. There is the court of Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the Embaſſadours, which are our <note place="margin">Mittimus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymas ad Deum Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos. Cypr.</note> teares and prayers. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſees twelue gates in heauen, al open, and all day open, to entertaine ſuitors repayring thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee that dwelleth in heauen</hi> is a word of terrour alſo. As out of a watch tower he beholds all ſecret and cloſe practiſes, no doores ſhut, no curtaine drawne, no parapet or wall to ſhelter, no vaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, no vault to couer; All thinges (ſaith the Apoſtle) are naked and bare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a word ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Anatomie. As when the skin
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20724:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> is flead and the fleſh pared away, all the inner parts are laid to ſight, ſuch are our actions to God. Man ſinnes, as if he had a <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 12. <hi>Qui ita nos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicit vt à nobis aſpici nequit, eo magis timendus, quo cuncta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens a nemine videtur. Greg. ſup.</hi> Iob <hi>ca.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>Giges</hi> ring to make him inuiſible: but when we are in darkeneſſe, God is in light, and by extramiſſion of his owne raies makes opacitie viſible. As if ſome lay hidden to intrap vs, but wee ſee him not, our caution is raiſed, and our feare doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: ſo ſhould our care and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction increaſe, who liue in the preſence of All-ſeeing God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee that dwelleth in the Heauens,</hi> Is a word of inſtruction. Earth is but a turfe for man to trample on, heauen is our home: heere we haue but boothes, there are the manſions, <hi>In my Fathers Houſe are manſions.</hi> No mortall <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itruuius</hi> can make an immortall habitation. The ſilly Spider may teach vs, who vpon the leaſt touch of her copweb; flits and remooues. The world is a copweb-world to bee ſwept downe with the broome of fire; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs ſo liue, as that we may liue and dwell with him who dwelleth in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20724:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> What does hee there at this time? <hi>Hee laughes.</hi> That is a hard word at the firſt view. Are the iniuries of his Saints, the cruelties of their enemies, the wicked enterpriſes againſt his anointed, matter of laughter? Laughter is a diminution of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Sopater. apud Stobaeum.</hi>
               </note> ſtate, as hee told Princes. Seuere <hi>Cato</hi> thought it became not the grauitie of a Roman Conſull, and is it attributed to the Maieſtie of heauen? There is a threefold Theologie or way to diſcourſe of God. 1. Negatiue, honouring him in ſilence, not daring, becauſe not able to expreſſe him, as when hee is ſaide to be inuiſible, incorporeall. Theſe Negatiues do ſecretly grant a more excellent knowledge, then can be attained, ſilence being the beſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence. 2. Affirmatiue, ſpeakes of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſerti multi Auſtin.</hi> 1. <hi>confeſſ. cap.</hi> 4.</note> God in few words, and thoſe of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as when he is ſtiled good, wiſe, iuſt. The firſt, like a Statuarie, hewes &amp; hacks out matter; the ſecond, as a painter, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and ſets it foorth in colours. The 3. way is Symbolicall, attributing al things to him which may make way to our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20724:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> as here laughter. Not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the point, how affections are ſaid to be in God; <hi>Nazianzen</hi> diſpatches it in one word, they are in him by Antiſtrophe or a conuerſion. Looke how man is affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Nazian. in Iamb.</hi>
               </note> when hee beholdes ſome Dwarfe buckling to grapple with a Giant: ſo our ſhallow capacitie, not able to expreſſe him otherwiſe, deſcribes him, as our ſelues would be, in a merry diſpoſition, deriding vaine attempts.</p>
            <p>Gods laughter importes theſe 4. parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. It expreſſes how eaſie and facile it is to the Almighty, euen at pleaſure with a ſmile, to ouerthrow wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, <hi>Ludit in humanis diuina potentia rebus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhewes the patience of God in his quiet forbearance, who could in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Poets fiction hath a graue morall. They faine lame <hi>Vulcan</hi> to be the Cutler of heauen, and Armour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker to their gods. The true God is ſlow to wrath, and vnwilling to puniſh, proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing his iudgements, expecting repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20724:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet ſo as by delaying, he brings his owne purpoſe to paſſe. Some times hee ſuffers them to deuiſe plots, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined that hee had found away by drowning the Iſraelites males, to root out their name from the earth: but did not God ſmile, when at the ſame time his owne daughter, in his owne court gaue princely education to <hi>Moſes</hi> their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer? <hi>Iulian</hi> ſuppoſed by rearing vp the Iewiſh ceremonies, to ſupplant the new <note place="margin">Iſoe. Eccleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiſt.</note> religion by the old, and therefore would be at the coſt to build the Temple againe: but did not God ſmile, when from vnder the foundations, as from <hi>Veſuuius</hi> hill, fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire brake foorth and diſſolued all his workes? Sometimes hee lets them make ſome progreſſe in their attempts. The Philiſtins ſurpriſe his owne Arke and carrie it away: but did not God ſmile, when their idoll <hi>Dagon</hi> tumled downe to doe it reuerence, and themſelues ſo tormented with ſickenes, as they were enforced to reſtore their pilfer with ſhame enough? When ſuperſtition and idolatry
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20724:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeeme to bee aduanced, the reſtauration tendes to the greater ruine. Is <hi>Dagon</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp to his place againe? ſhort is the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds ioy: Gods ſmile takes off his head and hands, leaues him neither wiſedome to guide, nor power to ſubſiſt.</p>
            <p>He permitted his Temple to be ſacked &amp; rifled, the holy veſſels to be prophaned and carouſed in; but did not Gods ſmile make <hi>Balthaſar</hi> to tremble at the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing vpon the wall! Oh what are his frownes, if his ſmiles bee ſo terrible! We may not iudge of Gods workes vntill the fift act, the caſe deplorable and deſperate in outward appearance, may with one ſmile from heauen finde a bleſſed iſſue.</p>
            <p>3 This laughter argues not ſo much what God doth, as what they ſuffer by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering and fruſtrating their practiſes, hee expoſeth them to ſcorne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Aboue hell there is not a greater puniſhment, then to become a <hi>Sannio,</hi> a ſubiect of ſcorne. <hi>Sampſon</hi> bare with more patience the boring out of his eyes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ludibrious ſcoffes of the Philiſtins.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20724:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Alcibiades</hi> did profeſſe, that neither the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his goods, nor his baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor the woundes receiued in his body, were ſo grieuous vnto him, as one ſcornefull word of his enemy <hi>Cteſiphon.</hi> Good Queene <hi>Eſter</hi> in her prayer to God for her people doth humbly deprecate this height of infelicity, <hi>O let them not laugh at our ruines;</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> holdes it for a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular token of Gods fauour; <hi>By this I know thou haſt a reſpect vnto mee, that mine enemie doeth not triumph ouer mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 Laſtly hee <hi>laughes,</hi> that is hee deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſes their prayers, and ſtops his eares when they call vpon him. A Chirurgion neuer cures a wound while the iron or ſteele remaine in it; nor doth God heare the ſuites of thoſe, whoſe will continues in ſin, whoſe thoughts are iron, ſteele &amp; gun-powder. They may conceiue prayers and take the Sacrament; but God highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, that his dreadful name &amp; holy inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be ſo prophaned. Praier is our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20724:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> bil of exchange, and is allowed in heauen, and returnes with what ſums of bleſſing we deſire, if agreeable to his wil. But when miſchieuous intentions appeare, God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts their bills, and proclaimes them bankrupts of his grace to all the world. So then <hi>Dauid</hi> hath found great oppoſition, but withall a ſure protection; men ſought his ouerthrow, God wrought their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. Rebellious doome is heauens ſcorne.</p>
            <p>One word of this text, as an Embleme to this day, ſhall giue a period to your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
            <p>This day, the fift of Nouember, a fatall inauſpicious day, branded in hiſtorie with a blacke coale for miſchiefe. Among the Grecians it was kept with ſad ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the loſſe of noble <hi>Aratus,</hi> the often <note place="margin">Plutarch. in rita Arati. Manlij Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darium.</note> preſeruer of his country. Among the Iewes famous for the ſlaughter of <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias</hi> the Prieſt, that day butchered in the temple, betweene the porch and the altar, our Sauiour vpbraiding the murder, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20724:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> yeeres after the fact. Among our ſelues neuer to be forgotten, a day for which we neede no Darius prompter, <hi>Memento Athenienſium;</hi> A day, <hi>quem ſemper acerbum, ſemper honoratum,</hi> as he ſaid of his fathers death day, euer to be thought vpon with ſadneſſe, and yet euer to bee remembred with ioy. For as <hi>Lucullus</hi> ſaid of a day ominous &amp; fatall, he would make it luckie and proſperous: ſo bleſſed be the change, God hath turned the funerall into a feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall. I wil not recount the well known ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, only I muſt put the <hi>Quare,</hi> why againſt our gracious Soueraigne? Could any complaine of his iuſtice? That is ſuch as it were not beſt for any greatneſſe to aduenture vpon. Or of his mercie? that is ſuch as his enemies neuer implored in vaine. Or of his vnquiet diſpoſition? he is the <hi>Neſtor</hi> of the times; <hi>Componere lites inter Peliden feſtinat, &amp; inter Atriden.</hi> Hee was euer, euer will be, the <hi>Noah</hi> of the age, borne to giue men reſt from their toiles and labours, the loadſtar of his actions
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20724:25"/> is peace: he hath alwayes called to the raging Chriſtians, as the moderate Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parte ciuibus</hi> Pompey.</note> Spare your blood, ſpend not that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally among your ſelues, which thrifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed, might ranſome your friends, and ruine your enemies. What cauſe then can you alledge? yes a colour; one fault his Maieſtie hath, which ſure he will neuer amend; the ſame fault which was found in <hi>Daniel</hi> long agoe: hee was ſo faithfull as no blame, no occaſion found, but onely in the worſhip and ſeruice of his God. That is the true <hi>Quare.</hi> His Maieſtie doeth not open his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes to the Romane Saints, but toward <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> aboue, and prayes to the God of Heauen. No roaring of Bulles can make him ſet vp an Idolatrous calfe, as <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> did: Hee will not erect Images, as <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> did; nor, to gratifie any forraigne Power, ſet vp an Altar, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the patterne of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> as <hi>Achas</hi> did; nor alter his Profeſſion for Affinitie, as <hi>Hemor</hi> and <hi>Sichem</hi> did. This was the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20724:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Quare</hi> of their malice, and withall of Gods mercie towards him. For as all Kings and Kingdomes are vnder the wings of Gods protection: yet thoſe principally, where his Church is foſtered, and his ſauing knowledge ſpread. It is his cuſtome, thoſe who promote his ſeruice, and take care of his holy buſineſſe, hee vſually prouids for their ſafetie. Doe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> goe vp to his ſolemnities, &amp; leaue their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey vnpeopled, to performe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? Tho Borderers bee prone to take occaſion of inlarging their Territorie,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quemque ſuae rapiunt ſcelerata ad proelia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luca.</note> 
               <hi>cauſae;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God will take away that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and itching appetite of incroching: no man ſhall deſire their land, no man dare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade them.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Quare</hi> bee asked for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Why raged they againſt it? The Text ſhewes, that the breaking of the Bands was their intention; there the Lawes were made which held them in awe.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20724:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> This Place where wee now are, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for a <hi>Quare:</hi> Why ſhould this ſtately Pile haue been demoliſhed, and not one ſtone left vpon another? This is <hi>Abrahams Mach-pelah,</hi> the burying Caue of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks, <note place="margin">Hierou. ad Marcel.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids Mauſolaeum,</hi> ſo <hi>Hierom</hi> called his Sepulchre, whereat hee was wont to pray: This is <hi>Solomons</hi> royall Recondito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, wherein were one and twente re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles, or Celles; as if in the ſpirit of Prophecie he had foreſeene, how many Kings ſhould be interred there, for iuſt ſo many in number, if you account from <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Zedechiah:</hi> This is <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Garden, a dedicated Cemetery, containing <hi>vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum decora alta parentum,</hi> the ſacred vrnes, and deare reliques of our famous decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Princes. <hi>Why did the heathen rage?</hi> For ſay the people were Chriſtian; yet the <hi>rage</hi> was heatheniſh, and barbarous aboue all madneſſe. The Lunaticke in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, who liued among the Graues, did not roote them vp.</p>
            <p>I end all: He that dwelleth in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20724:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> looked downe vpon vs, let vs looke vp to him: ſince by his mercy we liue and breath, let vs liue to breath Praiſe and Thankeſ-giuing vnto his Name. He hath neither zeale to Religion, nor loue to his Countrey, nor loyaltie to his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who this day binds not the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice with cordes to the hornes of the Altar; who this day ſends not vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſome incenſe of thanks. The Iewes once a yeere were wont to celebrate a Feaſt to ſorrow, wherein they went bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot, and with bitter imprecations they curſed <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian,</hi> for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Citie and Temple. I ſpeake confidently, <hi>fidenter quia fideliter;</hi> and I may ſay it without breach of any rule of charitie: Prieſts, Ieſuits, and all ſuch Romaniſts, as haue euill will at our Sion, this day doe keepe a feaſt to ſadneſſe, if not for griefe, that this hopefull Plot miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caried, yet for ſhame (vnleſſe they be paſt ſhame) that it was attempted. Let their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row increaſe our ioy; let our ioy increaſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20724:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> our Thankfulnes. As <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid of <hi>Phraa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> he was <hi>prius victus quam viſus:</hi> ſo this Conſpiracie againſt our <hi>Dauid,</hi> was knet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before it was fully hatched, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, but ouertaken, <hi>Hee that dwels in Heauen laught it to ſcorne.</hi> To him therefore, this day and euer, be aſcribed all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, praiſe, and glory. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20724:27"/>
            <p>LONDON, ¶ Printed by <hi>IOHN BILL. M. DC. XXII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
